Jack Milgrom Papers
Jack Milgrom Papers
1958-2005
Milgrom, Jack.
11.5 linear ft.
Collection consists largely of published material and reports collected and written by Jack Milgrom on the subjects of plastics in general, and specifically on the use of plastics in packaging and the recycling of plastics, as well as utility scrap and recycling in the auto industry.
2651142
Biographical History
Jack Milgrom was an American researcher and consultant in the plastics field. He received his A.B., M.S. and Ph.D. from the University of Chicago. He performed research in detergent, petroleum and elastomers, and worked in the plastics industry for Foster Grant among other companies. In 1968, Milgrom became a consultant with Arthur D. Little, Inc. and moved to SRI International in 1981. He then became the managing director of Walden Research, Inc. in 1983. Milgrom conducted seminars in the United States and Europe on plastics recycling, packaging and the environment.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jack Milgrom Papers consists largely of published material and reports collected and written by Jack Milgrom on the subjects of plastics in general, and specifically on the use of plastics in packaging and the recycling of plastics, as well as utility scrap and recycling in the auto industry.
Arthur D. Little reports contains documents and reports written by Milgrom and others at the company. Reports were written for private companies, industry trade groups, and government agencies, such as the Department of Health, Education and Welfare and the Food and Drug Administration.
Conference reports consists of proceedings from various national and international conferences on packaging, recycling, conservation, and waste management.
Printed materials consists of documents and reports written by other individuals, companies, agencies, and industry groups.
Research files contains folders assembled by Milgrom related to various projects with which he was involved. Of particular note in this content area are a series of documents related to the Committee on the Challenges of Modern Society, which was part of the North American Treaty Organization tasked in part with researching waste recycling in the late 1970s and early 1980s.
Writings contains published articles, speeches, and preparatory notes by Milgrom (exclusive of writing done under Arthur D. Little).
Arrangement of the Collection
Arranged into series by general topic.
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
Wiley Encyclopedia of Packaging Technology transferred to rare books for cataloging
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; Milgrom, Jack.; International Ryder Conference on Beverage Packaging.; Monsanto Chemical Company.; North Atlantic Treaty Organization. -- Committee on the Challenges of Modern Society.; Beverage containers.; Conservation of natural resources.; Container industry.; Food -- Packaging.; Packaging.; Plastics in packaging.; Plastics industry and trade.; Recycling (Waste, etc.); Recycling industry.; Biodegradable plastics.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Publications.; Reports.; Scrapbooks.; Technical reports.; Researchers.; Consultants.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from National Plastics Center and Museum, 11/06/2008. Originally, gift of Jack Milgrom.
Inventory
- Arthur D. Little reports
  - Aluminum two-piece food can: Industry’s reaction, 1976; report to Aluminum Company of America (Box 1)
  - Applications and markets for plastic wire coating scrap, 1973; report to Diversified Metals (Box 1)
  - Applications and markets for plastic wire coating scrap, 1975; report to Plastic Sales, Inc (Box 1)
  - Assessment of the fotential for Hercules’ oriented polypropylene bottle program, 1976; report to Hercules Inc (Box 1)
  - Attack on packaging, 1974; 1976; speech presented at The Fall Executive Conference of the National Flexible Packaging Association, Sept. 22 1976. also includes notes and newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Beverage container markets, manufacturing economics and recycling: Analysis of potential competition among can stock suppliers, 1980; report to Anaconda Aluminum Division by Robert A. Calef, Bruce M. Lane, Jack Milgrom, Elliott D. Novak, Edward L. Pepper, Paul R. Poston, and Frank M. Yans (Box 1)
  - Characterization of the plastics packaging industry, 1977; report to Owens-Illinois by Jack Milgrom, Elliot Novak, George Pickering, and Dewayne Whitehead (Box 1)
  - Commentary on plasticizer migration from polyvinyl chloride film, 1979; report to Department of Health, Education and Welfare (Box 1)
  - Development of a flameproof elastic elastomeric fiber, 1971; report to National Aeronautics and Space Administration (Box 1)
  - Energy requirements for plastic meat trays and egg cartons, 1978; report to Diamond International Corporation (Box 1)
  - Energy use patterns for metal recycling, 1978; report to U.S. Department of the Interior, Bureau of Mines (Box 2)
  - Energy utilized to deliver soft drinks in alternative containers in Ontario, 1983; report to Alcan Canada Products (Box 2)
  - Food contact polymers and polymer additives used in packaging, 1979; 2 folders; report to Food and Drug Administration. also includes draft report (Box 2)
  - Glass polymer composite sewer pipe: An initial evaluation of its commercial potential, 1979; report to Applied Science (Box 2)
  - Incentives for plastic recycling and reuse, 1970; report to Department of Health, Education and Welfare (Box 2)
  - Incentives for recycling and reuse of plastics, 1972; 2 folders; report for the Federal Solid Waste Management Program, Environmental Protection Agency. also includes draft report (Box 3)
  - Life cycle energy content of containers, 1982; report to The American Iron and Steel Institute (Box 3)
  - Life cycle energy requirements for selected sheet materials Applicable to manufacture of automobile components, 1979; report to The American Iron and Steel Institute (Box 3)
  - Migration of BHT antioxidant from high density polyethylene, 1981; report to Department of Health, Education and Welfare (Box 3)
  - Opportunities for a tire manufacturing plant in the Kuwait-Saudi Arabia region, 1978; report to Abdul-Aziz and Mohammad Aljomaih (Box 3)
  - Opportunities for regional solid waste management, 1975; report to The Regional Solid Waste Committee (Box 3)
  - Outlook for PVC and competitive materials in packaging food/pharmaceuticals/toiletries/cosmetics, part I, 1977; multi-client study (Box 3)
  - Outlook for PVC and competitive materials in packaging food/pharmaceuticals/toiletries/cosmetics, parts II and III, 1977; 2 folders; multi-client study (Box 4)
  - Packaging and economic growth, undated (Box 4)
  - Packaging for appliances and consumer electronic equipment: The environmental issue, 1973; report to Matsushita Electric Industrial Co (Box 4)
  - Packaging in perspective, undated; 2 copies (Box 4)
  - Polyvinylidene fluoride and ethylene-tetrafluoroethylene copolymers end-use markets/technology, 1972; report to Montecatini Edison (Box 4)
  - Potential diversification acquisitions, 1977; report to Uniroyal Chemical Company (Box 4)
  - Recovery of glass in North America, 1974; report by Milgrom presented at International Solid Waste Association Symposium at Montreal, Canada (Box 4)
  - State-of-the-art study of the pyrolysis of solid wastes, 1973; report to Combustion Equipment Associates, Inc (Box 4)
  - Status of plastics recycling in the USA, undated (Box 4)
  - Tinplate, aluminum and beverage container economics: A survey, 1979; report to Kaiser Aluminum and Chemical Corporation (Box 4)
  - Trends and opportunities in plastics recycling, 1991; report by Decision Resources, Arthur D. Little Affiliate (Box 4)
  - Vinylidene chloride monomer emissions from the monomer, polymer, and polymer processing industries, 1976; report to U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1972-1974; 1981; includes: Recycling Packaging Wastes in the U.S., newspaper clipping: US Urged to Spur Recycling of Plastics, Packaging Wastes, Resource Recovery, Recycling Scrap Thermoplastics (Box 5)
- Conference reports
  - Achieving Market Expansion Through Plastics Recycling, 1989; sponsored by The Institute for International Research (Box 5)
  - American Plastics Council: APC Durables Recycling Workshop II, 1998 (Box 5)
  - American Plastics Rouncil: APC Durables Recycling Workshop III, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Bev-Pak Americas, 1993 (Oversize 1)
  - Bev-Pak Americas, 1994 (Oversize 1)
  - Bev-Pak Americas speech, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Bev-Pak Americas, 1996 (Oversize 1)
  - Bev-Pak Americas, 1998 (Oversize 1)
  - Bev-Pak Americas personal notes and PowerPoint sheets, 1998 (Box 5)
  - Conservation and Recycling: Second World Recycling Congress, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Creating Environmentally Responsible Packaging (3rd annual conference), 1991 (Box 6)
  - Creating Environmentally Responsible Packaging (4th annual conference), 1992 (Box 6)
  - Food Product-Package Compatibility proceedings, 1986 (Box 6)
  - How to Design a Plastic Recycling Program: New England Resource Recovery Conference, 1990 (Oversize 1)
  - International Plastics and Rubber Planning Conference, 1989 (Box 6)
  - International Ryder Conference of Beverage Packaging (8th annual), 1984 (Box 6)
  - International Ryder Conference of Beverage Packaging (13th annual), 1989 (Box 7)
  - International Ryder Conference of Beverage Packaging (14th annual), 1990 (Box 7)
  - International Ryder Conference of Beverage Packaging (15th annual), 1991 (Box 7)
  - International Ryder Conference of Beverage Packaging (16th annual), 1992 (Box 7)
  - Plastics Recycling Business, 1994 (Oversize 1)
  - Plastic Recycling Workshop: Recycling Plastics in the 90s, 1989 (Oversize 2)
  - Profits in Recycling and Degradable Plastics: A Strategic Analysis Conference, 1990 (Oversize 1)
  - Recycling Law Reports from Raymond Communications, Inc, 1996; proceedings from take it back!: an international seminar for product and packaging makers (Oversize 2)
  - Recycling World Congress (2nd), 1979; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Regional Technical Conference: Plastics Disposal and Recycling, 1988 (Box 8)
  - Turn Waste Into Profits: An Integrated Approach to Plastics Management, 1992; proceedings from The Environmental Technology Exposition and Conference (Oversize 2)
- Printed materials
  - American Excelsior Company information, undated (Box 8)
  - Analysis of trends in municipal solid waste generation, 1992; report by Franklin Associates, Ltd (Box 8)
  - Application of technology-directed methods to reduce solid waste and conserve resources in the packaging of non-fluid foods, vol 1: A summary, 1978; prepared by Franklin Associates, Ltd for National Science Foundation (Box 8)
  - Aspects of plastic packaging waste management, 1993; report prepared by the Recycling Advisory Unit for the Environmental Unit DTI (Box 8)
  - Automobile shredder residue—the problem and potential solutions: An overview of the industry and problem and a review of potential methods for disposal, 1990; prepared by Robert J. Schmitt, Center for Materials Production (Box 8)
  - Beverage packaging systems—energy study, undated (Oversize 2)
  - Biodegradable polymer technology: Annual strategic report, 1996 (Box 9)
  - Business plan for the manufacture of composite-polymer durables from mixed, packaging-grade plastics, 1994 (Oversize 2)
  - Coca-Cola USA multi-material recycling manual, undated (Box 9)
  - Comparative energy and environmental impacts for soft drink delivery systems, 1989; report by Franklin Associates, Ltd for The National Association for Plastic Container Recovery (Box 9)
  - Congress R’95: Integrated resources management, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Curbside planning guide, 1989; guide by the Plastic Recycling Corporation of California to provide the basic PET (polyethylene terephthalate) recycling for city and waste management officials (Oversize 2)
  - Dispensing containers corporation confidential business plan, 1993 (Box 9)
  - Economic and environmental assessment of Alberta’s unique beverage container redemption system, 1983; report prepared by Michael J. Hare, economic and environmental consultant, for Waste Management Branch of Alberta Environment (Box 9)
  - Energy analysis of 10 oz soft drink packaging alternatives, 1976; prepared by S. E. Sax, of the Ontario Research Foundation (Box 9)
  - Energy utilized to deliver soft drinks in alternative containers in Ontario, 1983; report prepared by SRI International for Alcan Canada Products Ltd (Box 10)
  - Energy utilized to deliver soft drinks in alternative containers in Ontario: Executive summary, 1983; report prepared by SRI International for Alcan Canada Products Ltd (Box 10)
  - Environmental, economic, and energy impacts of material recovery facilities: A MITE program evaluation, 1995; report prepared by Roy F. Weston, Inc, and The Solid Waste Association of North America, funded by the Environmental Protection Agency (Box 10)
  - Environmental impact of plastics disposal in municipal solid wastes, 1986; technical report # 12 from Plastics Recycling Institute: A university-industry cooperative program (affiliated with State University of New Jersey Rutgers). project manager: Sidney Rankin (Box 10)
  - Facing America’s trash: What’s next for municipal solid waste?, 1989; 2 folders; report by U.S. Congress, Office of Technology Assessment in anticipation of the reauthorization of the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act. includes summary report (Box 10)
  - Facts and figures of the U.S. plastics industry, 1988; report by The Society of Plastics Industry, Inc (Box 10)
  - Family-size soft drink containers—a comparative energy and environmental analysis: Executive summary and vol. 1, 1978; 2 folders; prepared by Franklin Associates, Ltd for Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company Chemical Division (Box 10)
  - Family-size soft drink containers—a comparative energy and environmental impact analysis: Volume 2 – appendix, 1978; rrepared by Franklin Associates, Ltd. for Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company Chemical Division (Box 11)
  - Garbage, trash, refuse, waste, discards, rubbish, and junk (the book 3), 1994; report by Nichols Dezenhall Communications Management Group (Box 11)
  - Green products by design: Choices for a cleaner environment, 1992; report by U.S. Congress, Office of Technology Assessment (Box 11)
  - Growth markets for plastic bottles, 1986; report prepared by Technology Forecast for multi-client sponsorship (Box 11)
  - How government building codes and construction standards discourage recycling, 1996; part 3 of a series on recycling and deregulation: opportunities for market development, by Alexander Volokh of the Reason Foundation. also includes a press release (Box 11)
  - How to collect plastics for recycling, 1995; report by American Plastics Council; also includes press release (Box 11)
  - Making of steel, undated; report by American Iron and Steel Institute (Box 11)
  - Market study for Carborundum’s EKONOL thermoplastic polyester, 1991; report by Encotech for Carborundum Company (Box 11)
  - Microwave decade (the 1990s), 1989; report by Packaging Strategies (Oversize 2)
  - National post-consumer plastics recycling rate study (1993), 1994; report by R.W. Beck (Box 12)
  - National post-consumer plastics recycling rate study (1995), 1996; report by R.W. Beck (2 copies) (Box 12)
  - Pennsylvania municipal recycling sosts: Eight case studies, 1992; prepared by The Pennsylvania Soft Drink Association and Moore Recycling Associates for The Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Resources (Box 12)
  - Plastics: The energy saver, 1981; q summary report of an energy impact analysis of the manufacture and use of plastics products and equivalent products made from non-plastics alternative materials. report by Franklin Associates, Ltd. for The Society of Plastics Industry, Inc (Box 12)
  - Plastics and the environment: Progress and commitment, 1990; report by The Society of the Plastics Industry, Inc; author and editor: Bonnie Merrill Limbach (Box 12)
  - Plastics and the environment: Progress and commitment (2nd edition), 1991; report by The Society of the Plastics Industry, Inc; author and editor: Bonnie Merrill Limbach (Box 12)
  - Plastics industry in the year 2000, 1973; report prepared for The Society of the Plastics Industry, Inc. by R.L Glauz, Jr., A. G. Kridgl, R.H. Schwaar, and S.L. Soder. Stanford Research Institute (Box 12)
  - Plastics recycling foundation: Annual report, 1998 (Box 12)
  - Plastics recycling in the industrial sector: An assessment of the opportunities and constraints, 1989; report by Oak Ridge National Laboratory for the U.S. Department of Energy (Box 12)
  - Plastics recycling media packet, 1995; by the Freedonia Group, Inc (Box 12)
  - Plastic waste: Resource recovery and recycling in Japan, undated; report by Plastic Waste Management Institute (Box 12)
  - Polymer recycling, vol. 1, no. 4, 1994; journal edited by Michael E. Henstock. Includes a letter to Milgrom inviting him to submit a manuscript to the journal (Box 12)
  - Post-consumer mixed plastics recycling: Characterization, collection, costs and markets, 1991; report by Bruce A. Hegberg, William H. Hallenbeck, and Gary R. Brenniman. University of Illinois Center for Solid Waste Management and Research. Prepared for Illinois Dept. of Energy and Natural Resources (2 copies) (Box 12)
  - Recyling and reducing packaging waste: How the United States compares to other countries, 1991; report by James E. McCarthy, Congressional Resource Service report for Congress (Box 13)
  - Recycling venture forum study: Final report, 1995; report by David Kirkpatrick, Kirk Works (Box 13)
  - Report on measures for establishing the recycled plastics market (outline), 1975; report by Ministry of International Trade and Industry Committee on Plastics Waste Recycling (Box 13)
  - Review of the manufacturing process and characteristics of recycled plastic lumber, 1995; report by Dr. Prabhat Krishnaswamy and Dr. Duryodhan Mangaraj for Environment and Plastics Institute of Canada (Box 13)
  - Role of packaging in solid waste management 1966-1976, 1969; report written by Arsen Darnay and William E. Franklin, Midwest Research Institute, for the Bureau of Solid Waste Management (Box 13)
  - Santa Barbara county pilot waste collection project: Final report, 1994; a joint project of The Santa Barbara County Solid Waste Management Division, The National Audobon Society, and The Grocery Industry (Box 13)
  - Second materials: Engineering properties, environmental consequences, and social and economic impacts, 1993; prepared by Waste Management Institute, State University of New York at Stony Brook for The New York State Energy Research and Development Authority (Box 13)
  - Soft drink profitability study by package type: Final report, 1981; report by Booz-Allen and Hamilton Management Consultants for Can Manufacturers Institute (Box 13)
  - Source reduction of municipal solid waste in New York State: An INFORM study, 1995; report by Bette K. Fishbein (Box 13)
  - Specifications for materials recovered From municipal refuse, 1975; report by H. Alter and W. R. Reeves, The National Center for Resource Recovery, Inc. for U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (Box 13)
  - Statistical comparisons of USA rigid container market: Total vs. metal vs. glass vs. plastics 1972-1982 preliminary, 1983; prepared by Valerie B. Gigliotti (2 copies) (Box 14)
  - Table of energy requirements of some industrial processes, 1979; part 2 of the Handbook of industrial energy analysis (Box 14)
  - Technologies for recycling post-consumer mixed plastics: Plastic lumber production, emerging separation technologies, waste plastic handlers and equipment manufacturers, 1991; report by Bruce A. Hegberg, Gary R. Brenniman, and William H. Hallenbeck (Box 14)
  - Ten year review of plastics recycling, 1991; report by S.G. Howell for the Environmental Protection Agency (Box 14)
  - Use and disposal of plastics in agriculture, 1994; prepared by Amidon Recycling for the American Plastics Council, a joint initiative with The Society of the Plastics Industry, Inc (Box 14)
  - Value added to recyclable materials in the northeast, 1994; prepared by Roy F. Weston for The Northeast Recycling Council (Box 14)
- Research files
  - Auto plastics recycling, 1990-2003; newspaper clippings, Pheonix: Voice of the scrap recycling Industries, Automotive Report Series (3 issues) (Box 14)
  - Auto plastics recycling, 1994-1996; newspaper clippings, Dylark Plastics Recycling Technology brochure, press releases, Automative Report Series (3 issues) (Box 14)
  - Auto plastics recycling, 1997-2005; newspaper clippings, brochures: Hematite, Collins and Aikman, Automotive Aluminum Recycling (2), Ford Motor Company environmental annual report (May 1997) (Box 14)
  - Coca-Cola, 1982-1984; correspondences, presentations, handwritten notes, overhead projector sheets (Box 15)
  - Degradable plastic, 1985-1989; assorted newspaper clippings, communications and two brochures: "Ampacet’s answer to plastics degradability" and "Plastics for today’s technical problems and environmental concerns" (Box 15)
  - Degradable plastic, 1989-1994; assorted newspaper clippings, notes, and brochures (Box 15)
  - Degradable plastic, 1991-2003; assorted newspaper clippings, notes, and press releases (Box 15)
  - Degradable plastic: Cargill/Dow, 2001-2003; newspaper clippings (Box 15)
  - Degradable plastic: history, 1970-2003; Includes "A new chapter in degradable polymers" by Society of Plastics Industry (May 1997), e-mails, Environment and Plastics Industry Council newsletter, newspaper clippings, and magazine articles (Box 15)
  - NATO/CCMS: agenda, 1979; provisional agenda for meeting in Lisbon 1979. topic of meeting: implementing CCMS (Committee on the Challenges of Modern Society) pilot study on waste plastic recovery (Box 15)
  - NATO/CCMS: Appendices of first draft report of NATO/CCMS experts pilot study on waste plastic recovery, 1980; Prepared by George L. Ball (Box 15)
  - NATO/CCMS: appendices of meeting report, 1979 (Box 15)
  - NATO/CCMS: appendices of second draft report of NATO/CCMS experts pilot study on waste plastic recycling, 1980; prepared by George L. Ball (Box 16)
  - NATO/CCMS: meeting reports, 1979-1980; two reports: one from Lisbon in 1979 and one from The Hague in 1980 (2 copies) (Box 16)
  - NATO/CCMS: Waste plastic recycling information exchange, 1981; 2 folders; vols. 1 and 2. prepared by Monsanto Research Corporation (2 copies of vol. 1). also includes a letter from study leader Carl J. Schafer to the Experts Group on EPA letterhead (Box 16)
  - NATO/CCMS: Waste plastic recycling information exchange preliminary draft, 1980-1981; prepared by Monsanto Research Corporation. includes a letter from George L. Ball (pilot study chairman) to NATO/CCMS experts on plastic waste recycling, on Monsanto letterhead (Box 16)
  - NATO/CCMS: miscellaneous, 1977; 1979; communications, draft studies, articles (Box 16)
  - Packaging, 1984-1994; newspaper and magazine clippings, census reports (Box 16)
  - Packaging: market projections, 1981-1987; newspaper and magazine clippings, parts of a letter (Box 16)
  - Packaging: The silent servant, undated; photocopy of a paper: “Packaging... the silent servant… silent too long” (Box 16)
  - Recycling: Deposit State Experiences, 1977-1990; brochures, pamphlets, newsletters, and articles. Massachusetts and Michigan feature prominently (Box 16)